<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY app "Dell Recovery">
]>
<!--<?yelp:chunk-depth 4?>-->
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0
  Last modified: Mar 25, 2010
  Maintainers:
               Mario Limonciello <mario_limonciello@dell.com>
               
  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->
<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
  <!-- appropriate code -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Dell Recovery Manual</title>
    <!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2000</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

  -->
    <!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is
     not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the
     document.  -->
    <publisher>
      <publishername>Ubuntu Documentation Project</publishername>
    </publisher> 
    &legal;
    <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change
        any of this. -->
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Mario</firstname>
        <surname>Limonciello</surname>
        <email>mario_limonciello@dell.com</email>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <abstract>
      <para>Creating and using &app; Media.</para>
    </abstract> 
  </articleinfo> 
  <!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->

  <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="introduction">
    <title>What is &app; for?</title>
    <para>
      &app; can be used in the event that something disastrous happens
      to your computer causing it to not boot or perform as well as it did when
      first shipped to you.
    </para>
    <para>
      It's recommended that you create Recovery Media when you first receive a
      machine, mainly so you don't forget until it's too late.
    </para>
    <para>
      This tool can also be used to run recovery directly from the Hard Disk,
      for the event that you have done something bad to the system causing to
      perform suboptimally.  See <xref linkend="restoring-hdd"/> for details.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="create_mode">
    <title>Creating Recovery Media</title>
    <para>
      To create recovery media, select the first option in the &app;
      tool, titled "Build OS Media".  You will be asked what media type you want
      to create.  The tool will dynamically detect what your machine supports and
      only offer the appropriate type(s).
    </para>
    <figure id="media_types">
      <title>Possible Media Types</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/media_type.png"
                       format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>DVD, USB, ISO destination types</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The amount of time it takes to create the recovery media will depend on a
      variety of factors including but not limited to, system speed, memory quantity,
      other runnings applications, and target media quality.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you choose the "ISO" type media, the ISO image will be stored in your Downloads
      folder within your home directory.  You can burn it to a DVD using any standard DVD burning
      tools, and to a USB key using USB-Creator for Ubuntu.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="restoring">
  <title>Recovering your system</title>
  <para>
  This section of the document will walk you through how to recover your system
  from either the hard drive or recovery media that you previously created.
  </para>
    <sect2 id="restoring-hdd">
        <title>Recovering from the Hard Drive</title>
        <para>
          If you encounter a scenario that your machine is misbehaving, but your recovery partition is
          intact, you will be able to run the factory OS recovery from the hard drive.
        </para>
        <para>
          If your machine is able to boot up and log into the OS, select the "Restore System" option in
          the &app; tool.
        <figure id="welcome-figure">
          <title>&app; Welcome Screen</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/welcome.png"
                           format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
        </para>
        <para>
          If your machine is unable to boot up, press shift at the BIOS screen to bring up the Ubuntu bootloader.
          Select the last option on the list: "Restore Ubuntu to factory shipped state"
        </para>
        <figure id="grub-figure">
          <title>GRUB OS Chooser</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/grub.png"
                           format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
        <para>
          Either scenario will bring up the following confirmation screen before proceeding with recovery.
        </para>
        <figure id="hdd-recovery-figure">
          <title>HDD Recovery Confirmation Screen</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/hdd-recovery.png"
                           format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="restoring-dvd-usb">
        <title>Recovering from previously created recovery media</title>
        <para>
          If your machine is no longer booting and the recovery partition is not intact, you will be able
          to run the recovery from the DVD or USB media you created earlier.
        </para>
        <para>
        While booting your machine, press F12 at the BIOS post screen.  This will display a list of possible
        device.  Choose the appropriate media that you burned earlier.
        </para>
        <figure id="bios-device-figure">
          <title>HDD Recovery Confirmation Screen</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/boot_options.png"
                           format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
        <para>
        A Dell logo will appear.  Press enter to boot into the OS recovery wizard.
        </para>
        <para>
        You will be brought to a recovery screen allowing you to rebuild entirely to factory state, or to resize
        your existing OS install.  If you choose the second option, the installer will not build a 
        recovery partition, but will keep all data intact.
        </para>
        <figure id="usb-recovery-figure">
          <title>DVD and USB Recovery Screen</title>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/usb-recovery.png"
                           format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  <sect1 id="bto-media">
    <title>Build-to-Order (BTO) Custom Images</title>
    <para>
      The &app; tool includes an additional more advanced mode that allows
      you to apply additional granularity to the type of image that is generated.
      This mode can be used to insert additional drivers, and applications
      into the generated image.
    </para>
    <para>
      If your system does not contain a recovery partition, the tool will automatically
      launch in BTO builder mode.  If your system contains a recovery partition, but you
      want to forcefully launch in BTO builder mode, run the tool from command line like below.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Command line</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Execute the following command:
          <command>dell-recovery --builder</command></para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  <sect2 id="bto-base">
    <title>Base OS image</title>
    <para>
      The first page in BTO builder mode is the base OS image.  Normally you will want
      to select an Ubuntu ISO image to use.  It is recommended that you use a DVD or
      custom built ISO image.  This is because CD based images won't contain some proprietary
      drivers and language packages.  Due to this deficiency, there will be a reduced experience
      when using them.
    </para>
    <para>
      Alternatively, if you are running
      the tool on a system with a recovery partition, one of the available options
      will be to use that recovery partition for the base OS image.
    </para>
    <figure id="bto-base-figure">
      <title>Base OS Page</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/base_os.png"
                       format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="bto-fid">
    <title>Factory Install Development (FID) Overlay</title>
    <para>
      The second page in BTO builder mode is the FID overlay
      selection.  This is the special sauce that is added to all Ubuntu images to allow them
      to work properly in a Dell factory environment as well as a custom recovery solution on
      a customer's system.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are using a recovery partition or existing BTO image, you will be
      able to optionally skip this page and use the FID overlay included in the image.
    </para>
    <para>
      Otherwise, you will want to select the "FID framework enclosed in a debian package".  You will
      be able to either build the debian package from the currently running dell recovery version
      or provide a .deb from launchpad or a similar source.
    </para>
    <figure id="bto-fid-figure">
      <title>FID Overlay Page</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fid.png"
                       format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="bto-drivers">
    <title>Drivers</title>
    <para>
      The drivers page allows additional unconditionally installed drivers or
      scripts to fit into the OS installation process.  These can be in the form
      of Debian packages (debs) or specially crafted FISH packages that are designed
      to hook into the install process.  The details for these packages is out of the
      scope of this help guide however.
    </para>
    <figure id="bto-drivers-figure">
      <title>Drivers Page</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/driver.png"
                       format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="bto-applications">
    <title>Applications</title>
    <para>
      The applications page is only applicable to machines being installed within
      a factory environment.  It allows you to add applications that are tied to
      Service Release Vehicle identifiers (SRVs) so that they can be conditionally
      installed during factory process.
    </para>
    <para>
      One of the early steps of factory process will analyze the contents of System
      Descriptor Record (SDR) to see which SRVs were called out in the order.  The
      SRVs that are called out in the order will be included in the rest of the process.
      Any SRVs that were not called out in the order will be removed from the target system.
    </para>
    <para>
      When choosing to add an applicatin, you will be asked to provide the SRV associated with
      it.  Without accurately filling in this data, the process will not install these applications.
    </para>
    <figure id="bto-app-figure">
      <title>Applications Page</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/application.png"
                       format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
